Finding Aid for Theophil Henry Hildebrandt Papers 1887-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Theophil Henry Hildebrandt Papers 1887-1978, 1930-1960
Hildebrandt, Theophil Henry, 1888-
6 linear feet
Mathematician, professor of mathematics at the University of Michigan. Correspondence and other papers relating to professional and family matters, to his association with the Bethlehem Church in Ann Arbor, and to his involvement with the American Mathematical Society, especially regarding the controversy over loyalty oaths in the 1950s; also letters from family members, notably sister Martha, a school teacher, who comments on her career and her life as a single woman; and letters from son Paul during World War II; and photographs.
85205 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Hildebrandt's son, Dr. H. Mark Hildbrandt (donor no. 3466 ) and came to the library in April 1983.
The collection is open for research.
Theophil Henry Hildebrandt was born July 24,1888 in Canal Dover, Ohio. His parents, German nationals (although his mother had been born in West Africa), were Basel missionaries in Africa. Following their marriage, they left the mission field and immigrated to the United States.
After the birth of Theophil, the Hildebrandt family moved from Ohio to Bellewood, Illinois. Young "T.H." Hildebrandt was something of a prodigy. After completing high school in three years, he entered the University of Illinois at the age of fourteen, earning his B.A. degree in mathematics in 1905. He received both an M.S. (1906) and a PhD (1910) from the University of Chicago before he turned twenty-one.
In 1909 Hildebrandt came to Ann Arbor as an instructor in mathematics. His rise in the department was steady. He was an assistant professor by 1914, an associate in 1920, and became a full professor in 1923. Hildebrandt was appointed chairman of the department of mathematics in 1934, and he retained this position until he retired in 1957. He was also the supervisor for research projects in pure mathematics sponsored by the Office of Naval Research.
Hildebrandt's interests in mathematics included the theories of integration, integral equations and linear spaces. He published one textbook Introduction to the Theory of Integration (New York and London; Academic Press, 1963), and wrote numerous articles and reviews.
Hildebrandt won the Chauvenet Prize for an outstanding article in 1929. In addition, he was an elected member of Phi Beta Kappa, Sigma Xi (President of the Michigan Chapter), and Phi Kappa Phi. In 1963, the University of Michigan created the "T.H. Hildebrandt Research Instructorships" for young mathematicians. These were later changed to assistant professorships in 1974.
Other affiliations of his included the American Association for the Advancement of Science (vice-president, 1935), the American Mathematical Society (vice-president, 1924-1926), the Mathematics Association of America (vice-president, 1937), the National Research Council, the National Council of Mathematics Teachers, and the Societe' Mathematique de France. From 1938 to 1942, Hildebrandt was an editor for the American Journal of Mathematics. He was also a president of the University of Michigan Research Club, and before his marriage (to Dora Ware, 1921), he was a member of the Apostles, a University club consisting of no more than twelve unmarried faculty men. He was also a member of the Pleasant Lakes Club.
In addition to mathematics Hildebrandt had a life-long passion for music. Shortly after becoming an instructor in 1909, he enrolled in the University of Michigan School of Music. In 1913 he received a B.A. in organ performance. From 1913 to 1917 he was the organist and choir director of the First Congregational Church of Ann Arbor. As a result of anti- German sentiment expressed toward him by this church during the First World War, Hildebrandt left and became the organist for the Bethlehem United Church of Christ, also in Ann Arbor.
Even after Hildebrandt retired from the University of Michigan in 1957, he continued to teach one year stints at other universities, and maintained an active interest in mathematics until he was quite old. He died October 9,1980 at the age of ninety-two.
The papers of T.H. Hildebrandt consist of six linear feet of materials spanning the years 1887 to 1978. The bulk of the collection falls between the years 1930 and 1960. The papers have been arranged in ten series: Biographical Material, Bethlehem Church, Compositions, Correspondence, Lectures, Notes, Organizations, Universities, Writings, and Visual Materials.
As Hildebrandt was fairly well known in his field, he corresponded with other eminent mathematicians of his time, including Eliakim Hostings Moore (with whom he had studied) and Maurice Frechet. The Hildebrandt papers are also valuable for other topics: the development of mathematical ideas and the various pressures placed on academics during the Cold War to name both two examples.
Subjects:
American Mathematical Society.; Bethlehem United Church of Christ (Ann Arbor, Mich.); German Americans--Michigan.; Hildebrandt, Theophil Henry, 1888-; Loyalty oaths.; Mathematics.; Teachers--United States.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Mathematics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Women teachers--United States.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Churches.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Ann Arbor School of Music. Class of 1913.; Apostles Club (University of Michigan); Bethlehem United Church of Christ (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Douglas Lake (Mich.); Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Hildebrandt, Theophil Henry, 1888-; Hildebrandt family.; University of Michigan. Biological Station.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Mathematics.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1951-1960.; Ware family.
Contributors:
Hildebrandt, Martha.; Hildebrandt, Paul.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical Material
  Biographical Material is subdivided into general material about Hildebrandt, awards and appointments, clippings, collected material on other family members, genealogy (which includes the Hildebrandt, Locher and Ware families), and material relating to his military service in the First World War.
  - General (Box 1)
  - Awards/Appointments (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1934-1962 (Box 1)
  - Collected Materials (on family members) (Box 1)
  - Genealogy
    - Hildebrandt family (Box 1)
    - Locher family (mother's side) (Box 1)
    - Ware family (wife's side)
      - Diaries 1887, 1910-1914 (Box 1)
      - History (Box 1)
  - Military Service (Box 1)
- Bethlehem Church
  The Bethlehem Church series contains constitution and membership material, correspondence, financial reports and programs. The series covers the years 1928-1967.
  - Constitution and Membership (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1934-1957 (Box 1)
  - Financial Reports
    - October 1926-September 1941 (Box 1)
    - October 1941-December 1958 (Box 1)
  - Programs 1928-1967 (Box 1)
- Compositions, Musical
  The Compositions consist of musical works copied out in Hildebrandt's hand. The compositions are religious, and not all of them are original.
  - Religious musical compositions (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence is the largest part of the collection. This series was broken down into smaller subseries. The first of these is a European travelogue from 1926, which consists of a set of letters from Hildebrandt to his brothers and sisters during a year-long sojourn in Europe. Next comes a subseries of letters of recommendation, followed by a lengthy personal section. This includes letters from his father during the First World War (written in German), letters from his sister Martha, and letters from his son Paul during the Second World War. Hildebrandt's sister was an unmarried schoolteacher, who first taught German. and then after the outbreak of WWI, mathematics. Her letters, which are quite numerous, run from 1914 to 1970. Letters dated after 1970 were not retained because their historical value diminished substantially as Ms. Hildebrandt grew older. The final subseries contains T.H. Hildebrandt's professional correspondence from 1906 to 1978.
  - European Travelogue 1926 (Box 1)
  - Letters of Recommendation
    - 1956-1958 (Box 1)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 1)
    - 1961-1966 (Box 1)
  - Personal
    - From father 1916-1918 (Box 1)
    - To sister, Martha 1917-1920 (Box 1)
    - From sister, Martha
      - 1914-1917, 4 folders (Box 1)
      - 1918-1970, 21 folders (Box 2)
    - From son Paul, World War II 1944-1946 (Box 2)
  - Professional
    - Undated 1906-1953, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - 1954-1978, 13 folders (Box 3)
- Lectures
  - "On Integration" 1949 (Box 3)
  - "Linear Spaces" 1949-1950 (Box 3)
- Notes (mathematics)
  The Notes, most of which were taken by Hildebrandt as a student, have been arranged chronologically by year and semester. Where possible, the course name is also given.
  - Undated
    - Integral Equations (Box 3)
    - Limits and Continuity (Box 3)
    - Sequences (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - 1905
    - Differential Geometry (Box 3)
  - 1906
    - Winter
      - Mechanics (Box 3)
    - Spring
      - Definite Integrals (Box 3)
      - Plane Vectors and Conjugate Functions (Box 3)
    - Summer
      - Projective Geometry (Box 3)
  - 1907
    - Fall
      - General Analysis (Box 4)
      - Integral Equations (Box 4)
      - Modern Analytic Geometry (Box 4)
    - Winter
      - Elliptic Functions (Box 4)
      - Higher Plane Curves (Box 4)
    - Spring
      - Invariants (Box 4)
    - Summer
      - Calculus of Variations (Box 4)
      - Determinants (Box 4)
  - 1908
    - Winter
      - Calculus of Variations (Box 4)
      - Partial Differential Equations (Box 4)
    - Spring
      - Celestial Mechanics Periodic Solutions (Box 4)
  - 1909
    - Unidentified (Box 4)
    - General Analysis, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Differential Equations (Box 4)
  - 1910 Vector Analysis (Box 4)
  - 1916-1917 (Box 4)
  - 1924-1936 (Box 4)
  - 1929 Real Variables (Box 4)
  - 1929-1930
    - Function Theory (Box 4)
    - Integration (Box 4)
  - 1932 Theory of Integers (Box 4)
  - 1932-1933 Function Theory (Box 4)
  - 1944-1964 (Box 4)
- Organizations
  The next series, Organizations, is arranged alphabetically. The greatest amount of material here concerns the American Mathematical Society. There is some interesting material relating to the Loyalty Oath required of professors by the University of California in 1950. The American Mathematical Society (AMS) took a civil liberties stance against the Oath, and resolved to hold no meetings in California until the situation was rectified. Hildebrandt submitted a minority report opposing this action by the AMS. He claimed that by involving itself in relations between an employer and its employees the AMS was behaving more like a union than an organization dedicated to scholarship.
  - American Mathematical Society
    - Committees
      - Loyalty Oath 1950-1951 (Box 5)
      - Special Funds 1938-1944 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence 1931-1963 (Box 5)
    - General Business
      - 1917-1935 (Box 5)
      - 1936-1948 (Box 5)
  - Apostles (Box 5)
  - Mathematical Association of America 1935, 1965 (Box 5)
  - Pleasant Lakes Club 1927-1943 (Box 5)
  - Sigma Xi 1942-1945 (Box 5)
- Universities
  The Universities series is arranged alphabetically and concerns Hildebrandt's dealings with Louisiana State, Marquette, Memphis State, Northwestern University, the University of Michigan, North Carolina, Utah and Western Michigan. The subseries on the University of Michigan is the most substantial, including Employment Records, Correspondence and Memos relating to the Department of Mathematics, material from the Research Club, and a eulogy of Alexander Ziwet.
  - Louisiana State University 1960-1961 (Box 5)
  - Marquette University 1958-1963 (Box 5)
  - Memphis State University 1958-1959 (Box 5)
  - Northwestern University 1964-1965 (Box 5)
  - University of Michigan
    - Employment Records 1909-1958 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence and Memos 1933-1961 (Box 5)
    - Department of Mathematics, PhD's-- 1912-1960 (Box 5)
    - Research Club 1937-1956 (Box 5)
    - Ziwet, Alexander-Eulogy (Box 5)
  - University of North Carolina 1958-1962 (Box 5)
  - University of Utah 1961-1970 (Box 5)
  - Western Michigan University 1961-1962 (Box 5)
- Writings
  Writings includes a bibliography of Hildebrandt's writings, two folders of drafts, and material pertaining to an article he wrote for an encyclopedia. Included are reprints of his writings, reviews, and his B.A., M.S. and Ph.D. theses.
  - Bibliography (Box 5)
  - Drafts, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Encyclopedia article 1944-1945 (Box 5)
  - Reprints
    - Undated (Box 5)
    - 1908-1918 (Box 5)
    - 1920-1929 (Box 5)
    - 1930-1966 (Box 5)
  - Reviews (by T.H.)
    - Undated (Box 5)
    - 1931-1937 (Box 5)
    - 1943-1959 (Box 5)
    - 1960-1976 (Box 5)
  - Reviews (of T.H.) 1964 (Box 5)
  - Theses and Dissertation
    - B.A., "The Hyperbolic Functions" 1905 (Box 5)
    - M.S., "The Limit Surfaces of Linear Congruences" 1906 (Box 5)
    - Ph.D., "A Contribution to the Foundations of Frechet's Calcul Fonctionnel" 1912 (Box 5)
  - Miscellanea (Box 5)
- Visual Materials
  Visual Materials includes both loose photographs and personal albums. Included are portraits and family photos; photos of activities of the University of Michigan Department of Mathematics, and the University of Michigan Biological Station; and photos of Hildebrandt family homes, Bethlehem Church in Ann Arbor, Michigan, and the Class of 1913 of the University of Michigan.
  - Photographs
    - Apostles Club (Box 6)
    - Churches, choirs and organs (Box 6)
    - Family
      - Early, before World War II (Box 6)
      - Late, after World War II (Box 6)
    - Homes-mostly Ann Arbor but some miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Portraits (Box 6)
    - Pleasant Lakes Club (Box 6)
    - Professional Groups and colleagues--includes parties and University of Chicago Math Department in 1920 (Box 6)
    - University of Michigan Buildings and University School of Music Class Photograph 1913 University School of Music (Box 6)
      (see also albums)
    - University of Michigan. Department of Mathematics. (Box 6)
    - University of Michigan. Department of Mathematics-Student skit (Box 6)
    - Ware family of Grand Rapids, Mich. (Box 6)
  - Albums
    - Small black album 1895-1920 (Box 6)
      (includes early schooling, family and trip to Germany in 1926. Also shows early life in Ann Arbor, the UM School of Music, Apostles Club, UM campus buildings, homes on Washtenaw, Elm, Walnut and Monroe Streets in Ann Arbor, and organs in churches in Chelsea and Ann Arbor. Some early scenes in Illinois and Ohio as well.)
    - Small black album 1915-1920 (Box 6)
      (includes family and friends and early days at the University of Michigan; and views of campus buildings, scenic views of Ann Arbor and the Biological Station at Douglas Lake; also included are the wedding of Grace McDonald and Carl Guthe, Kansas City, and other travels)
    - Brown album, entitled "Professor and Mrs. T. Hildebrandt" circa 1960 (Box 6)
      (Album consists of photographs of colleagues and friends from1919 to 1956, his years at Michigan, and was presented to him upon his retirement from the University, includes some photographs of Hildebrandt teaching in classroom)
    - Red album. Title: "Department of Mathematics Christmas, December 1955. Presented to Dr. Hildebrandt, Compliments of the Department and the Photographer, Jim Wendel, August 2, 1957" (Box 6)
      (cover broken, includes photos of student skit)